So you're putting out content online,
and for some reason, the amount of views
you're getting aren't in line with how
good the content is that you've put out.
You think maybe you need to pay for a blue
tick, maybe the algorithm's against you,
maybe you're being punished for being a
smaller channel, but the reality is a
little bit more depressing.
When it comes to exceeding 10,000 views on
every single video that you put out,
there are some harsh rules that we need to
come to terms with.
But the first reality we need to come to
terms with is that
every single social media platform wants
you to win.
It doesn't just want your video to get
10,000 views, it wants it to get 100,000,
a
million, maybe even a billion views.
But there's a problem.
Your videos just aren't good enough to do
that. Think about YouTube, for instance.
YouTube quite literally splits the money
it makes with you.
Every single view on your video,
you make money, they make money.
Why wouldn't they want your video to reach
massive amounts of people?
Your experience on a platform
is dictated by the level of content
that you get.
If you were served rubbish videos on
TikTok, you're going to leave and go to
Instagram. Vice versa,
if you go onto Instagram
and you're getting all these
cookery videos when you don't even cook,
you're going to leave and go somewhere
else. Next thing you know,
you're on Twitter, or X.
So the first belief we must deconstruct,
it's not an external thing, it's an
internal thing.
If your videos aren't performing, it
is going to be down to the
quality of those videos. Now,
this doesn't mean an overhaul.
It doesn't mean that you need to
revolutionize who you are
or how you go about
making content.
You just need to play the game.
Many content creators all have their own
ideas of how the algorithm works, but I'm
going to break it down in the most
simplistic of ways.
The first thing to imagine
is an inverted pyramid.
In the onset,
a very small amount of people
are going to be shown your videos,
probably your biggest fans
or the people that have engaged with your
content
recently.
If the last time you saw a content creator
and you watched more than
75% of their video,
when the next one comes out,
you're going to be served it.
So whatever social media algorithm it is,
they're going to show a small amount of
people your video.
Then they're going to look at the reaction
that comes from that.
How many of them watched it towards the
end? How many people left?
How many people had a positive engagement
with it? How many people didn't like it?
If the first piece of
that inverted pyramid looked good,
it goes to the next bit,
from warmer to colder,
from top fans to people
that only occasionally watch your
content. And as the audiences get colder,
if the engagement and the
likes and the average view duration
are still remaining good, it's going to
keep getting shown a wider
and wider audience.
And if people that have never seen your
content before start vibing with what
you've put out, that's
when you're going head first towards being
viral.
So let's backtrack quickly
and look at average view duration.
So whether your reel is 60 seconds,
two minutes,
or it's a YouTube video that's 25
minutes long, even on YouTube,
this platform right now,
one of the biggest things
that people are looking for
is average view duration.
How long do you watch a video for? This
is one of the big reasons I stopped
sharing
my YouTube videos to Instagram,
because I was sending traffic to YouTube,
and when
they get there to a 12-minute video,
they're in the wrong place of mind to be
engaging and watching it the whole way
through.
I will use Instagram and TikTok
when I'm having a poo.
But if I'm then sent to YouTube,
and it's a 28-minute video,
even my longest poos
don't take that long,
I'm leaving the video after three minutes.
I forget about it, and I never go back.
To YouTube, to the algorithm, it goes,
"Oh, this guy went to watch a 28-minute
video. He only watched three minutes.
It can't be that good of a video." We even
have the analytics that we can see
inside Instagram to see what
is the average amount of time someone
is watching our
video. Although it's worth noting,
YouTube and short-form content creation
are very
different in these ways,
because people didn't opt to see it on
short-form content creation. They
were served it.
Whereas on YouTube,
people click the title and thumbnail.
It's not like it was sprung up on them
without them knowing.
So the average view duration
is a little bit more accurate on YouTube,
because you
know that person was semi-ripe for the
video, or they wouldn't have clicked it.
Whereas in short-form content creation,
people might have been served it.
There might have been something
that they were just trying to figure out
in the
early part of your video.
If your average view duration
is not good enough, you are
not retaining people, and
if you're not retaining people,
you have a big problem.
Retention is easiest described as keeping
people interested, and better yet, even
just getting people interested in the
first place. This is why we use a hook.
In YouTube, we use an introduction,
and that introduction
is going to pay off the
title and thumbnail
that they've just clicked on.
For instance, you'll notice
that for this video,
I start talking about the problems
that you face. Being a small account
and not getting the views you want.
I'm paying off the title
and thumbnail that you clicked.
But when it comes to short-form content
creation, we almost need to package those
things into the very introduction of the
video, and there are different hooks that
we can use. Question hooks.
Did you know that walking
is better for fat loss than
running? Statement hooks. There
is 3,500 calories in this pot of Pringles.
Preview hooks,
where you show something that's coming
later in the video, and even
visual hooks. The iPhone 15
is better than the iPhone 16, and in this
video, I'm going to tell you why.
So let's consider
that average view duration is
something that's very important to us.
It's also why at the end of some of my
YouTube videos, I will point people to
another video. Yes,
because I want to help them,
and I want them to be educated
with the next series,
but mostly because
if I get scored highly on average view
duration, YouTube's going to go, "Yo,
there are people out there watching this
guy
that always wears vests talk about social
media, and they're staying.
And if they're staying on platform
and they're watching multiple videos,
let's take
colder audiences and give them to James."
Engagement is another way that we
can get our videos taken up
that inverted pyramid
that little bit further.
Because even if that video has only been
shown to a small amount of people, but
they're commenting, they're engaging,
they're asking questions,
maybe even they're
in outrage.
I didn't even realize the implications I
was going to have the other
day when I spoke about roll-on deodorant.
I hate roll-on deodorant.
This, as a means of applying
deodorant, just seems archaic,
something a Neanderthal would use.
It's wet. It's drippy. You get this
[squishing noise] when you open
and close your armpit.
It smells great, but there
are better ways to apply it.
When I say aerosol, everyone's like,
"The environment."
And the connotation that I
had was pretty much,
if you're still using roll-on in 2024,
you're a mouth
breather,
and you should've been brought up better.
There was outrage in the comments.
"What's wrong with roll-on?
Why can't I use roll-on?"
And the engagement,
I didn't even mean to engagement
bait, the engagement in that video
was massive.
We got a million views in 24 hours.
So if you can get people to engage with
the video you're putting out, similar to
the Coke Zero and Pepsi Max debate.
Some people out there, maybe they
were dropped as a child on their head,
or maybe
deprived of oxygen as a baby, think
that Pepsi Max tastes better than Coke
Zero,
which is another tangent altogether.
Quite literally,
you can go to any restaurant
or establishment, "Oh, can I have a
Coke Zero,
please?" "We've only got Pepsi Max." You
might as well insult my mum and
dropkick my nan in the back of the head
because that's how bad it is
that you can't
even have Coke Zero. Pepsi Max,
it's disgusting.
So we have average view duration that's
important, but also if we can get more
engagement out of people, not by saying,
"DM the word success," or
not. Just put something in your video,
maybe contrarian, maybe controversial,
something that you believe in,
something that you think is right.
Not to engagement bait,
but just to give people the opportunity to
give their input on it. Another thing
that helps with engagement
is people sending
posts to each other.
Some videos you will see have more people
sending it.
That's why we get the visual
representation of the little paper
airplane.
More people sending it than there have
been comments or likes on it.
So if you have something that's compelling
to get people to send to their friends,
like the Coke Zero debate, everyone
that watched my video on that, I think the
reason it did so well
and got so many millions of views
is they sent it to, one,
their Pepsi Max friends, and two,
people that thought that Coke Zero
was going to
kill them.
If you can tap into these things,
you can do so much better when it
comes to views and success on social
media, which we'll get into briefly.
So your content has to be engaging.
If you pick boring things to talk about,
"Is it true that running trainers are the
worst type of footwear to wear in the
gym?" People are going to be gone.
It's going to bring me into the next part
of this video.
Understand the behaviors of the people
watching your content at that given time.
Most people
I'm only going to give you a few seconds.
This was me when I used to use Hinge back
in the day.
You make your mind up in literally a
couple of seconds,
and they're doing the same
for you. So you need to capture them.
You need to put something interesting,
say something.
You are trying to peacock in a crowded
room at this point.
And if you can understand the behaviors of
that person on the platform, you can
engage with them better,
whether it's using a prop.
You're wrong about roll-on deodorant,
and this is why.
There's another thing,
just on a side tangent, that I think
is engagement killing
at the moment, and it's
when people start videos going, "Here
are 11
ways that you..." Gone,
because you're boring.
In this video,
I'm actually going to give you 11 ways to
do it.
But I didn't say that in the introduction.
I just started giving you information,
and hopefully I'll retain you because
every
single one that I say, you're like, "Oh,
that's actually quite clever.
I didn't think of
that before." One of the biggest things
that is really ruining a
lot of people on social media at the
moment is just having poor audio quality.
You should be using professional
microphones, not these little
clip-on ones that I've seen.
If I quite literally type in "cheap
wireless
microphone" into Amazon,
these little ones come up
that literally sound
worse than your iPhone. So
when you've got your phone in front of you
and you're
recording reels,
it quite literally would sound better
if you didn't
have that microphone on. Here,
I'm using a professional podcast
microphone because, to me, it matters.
Audio quality matters.
Over there, I've got DJI mics, which are a
prerequisite for most content creators.
If your audio sounds rubbish,
people will leave.
If you can't even respect the aural
experience, aural as in
A-U-R-A-L, not oral as [gulps] .
Do you use the word oral
at all? A-U-R-A-L.
Let me just check what that means.
A-U-R-A-L.
What does that mean? Relating to ear
or sense of hearing. Every day
is school day.
Why they made that the same word as oral
for... I don't make the rules.
Video quality is also important.
Although you can make amazing content on
an iPhone,
you can make amazing content on a DJI
Pocket Osmo 3, you can make
amazing content on a lot of things.
As you improve and get better,
so should your setup.
Two videos ago on this channel,
the auto-focus on my camera went out a few
times,
and to be quite frank, it
was quite embarrassing.
When I would move my finger close to the
camera, I would go out of focus.
But as you see today, ladies
and gentlemen, that does not happen. Why?
Because I spent $10,000 on camera
and equipment.
Should you be doing that? No.
But as your business grows
and your brand evolves, so
should the level of quality
that you put out.
With everything you do,
you should overpromise and overdeliver.
And even now, I'm just rambling here,
trying to give you some advice on how to
break that 10,000 mark on all your video
views.
And I'm here respecting you,
giving you good quality audio,
making this a visual masterpiece,
because I care.
And if I care this much about this,
imagine how good my course will be.
There's a link in the description.
You relax. Keep your pants on, love.
The next thing you need to be considerate
of if you really want to bolster the
things we've spoken about
is going the extra mile with things like
B-roll.
I'm going to get Declan in the edit right
now to overlay footage of me doing other
things just because it'll look quite nice
for this segment.
We could have actually just filmed some
B-roll of me and my...
I'll tell you what,
let's make it easier for Declan now.
So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to verbally say something,
and I'm going to
give you a visual,
and we're going to overlay it together,
and it's going to look
sexy as fuck.
Do you ever find yourself scrolling away
on social media feeling like
you're just scrolling your life away,
but it's just so good, and all the people
that you see on social media just look so
sexy, and then suddenly you get served
girls with mad bundas,
and then you feel like,
"What am I doing in my life?" There
are other things you can do,
like pattern interrupt,
where you can move the tripod
between different scenes
that you're filming.
Even just turning it a little bit on an
angle could keep you more engaged.
Some people, even
when they're filming themselves,
will invert the camera
from left to right,
just so it looks like you're in a slightly
different setup.
We'll do it right now,
and suddenly the light
is on the other side compared to
usual. Well, actually,
it's going to be on this side,
just on the other side.
And the best content creators
are very good at telling stories.
They have setups.
They have payoffs. They raise the stakes.
Within the last 48 hours, Matt Armstrong,
one of my favorite YouTubers, tried to
rebuild an Aston Martin DB12 in 24 hours.
He doesn't have to do that in 24 hours.
He can take his time.
It's a crash-damaged car.
He can do whatever the hell he wants with
it.
There is actually no time restraints for
But by saying 24 hours,
it keeps people engaged.
And the whole way through
that one-hour video,
they keep showing the stopwatch.
We've only got eight hours left.
We've only got six hours left.
That is a fabrication of something just to
keep you engaged that little
bit more because the question pending in
your mind the entire time is, are they
going to be able to do it?
And one of the biggest lessons
when it comes to really
bolstering the amounts of views
and virality that you get is this.
Stop trying to carve a new path in content
creation in the
direction of where you think amazing
content's going to be.
There are so many examples of things
that have worked well right in front of
you.
I am using a long-winded way of saying
copy what's working.
Because if you're a small account, 500,
1,000, maybe even 2,000 subscribers, guess
what? The road to the top is a very,
very long way, and
if you want to make that
way a little bit easier, copy people.
You think I made up the calorie deficit?
You think I came up with half the hooks
that I use?
You think that the thumbnail for this
is original? It's not.
I haven't even made the thumbnail yet,
which goes against one of my golden rules
of
YouTube, but we'll get into
that in later videos.
But I am looking and seeing at what works,
and I'm making my own version of it.
Even this business, The Mentorship,
is four to five other
businesses that I've used over the years
brought together.
But then I know the people that
were in the businesses that I
was a part of were
probably in someone else's.
If you see a good hook,
if you see a good setup, if you
see a good payoff, make it your own.
Don't copy it word for word.
Make it your own.
If you see a good title and thumbnail,
you can copy it one for one.
I'll give you an example right now.
This was supposed to be a five-minute
video, Declan.
If I go to my videos on YouTube,
in the middle, you will see a video,
"The number
one exercise to lose belly fat,"
and you'll notice there
is me with my belly out,
next to me sucking it in. Imagine if
that video existed
on YouTube already. Number two in
that list,
"The number one exercise to lose belly
fat." I stole the title and thumbnail.
I didn't even watch the video.
I just stole the title and thumbnail.
That's how I knew I wouldn't get done for
plagiarism because I quite literally
didn't watch that. There
was another video
that I did on metabolism, and someone
commented on that video, "It's clear
that someone watched Jeff Nippard's video
on
meta..." Of course I did. Because
if I'm going to do a video on a topic,
you don't
think I'm going to go watch the
top-performing videos in that niche
and take the
best bits? If you want to break through,
I'm not saying do it every video,
but if you want to emerge,
if you want to get eyes on you,
you sometimes need to
copy what's working. MrBeast, Ryan Trahan,
the best and
biggest YouTubers on the planet do the
exact same thing.
Everyone is out here copying each other.
There are people
that have copied my posts
that made more money than me.
They're not going to send the lawyers.
And as a small account,
what would be the point? What
are they going to do?
Sue you and take your student loan?
Once in a while,
when you really need to throw petrol on
the fire, do it.
I'm giving you full permission not to copy
people's content, but to steal their
good ideas and make them better.
Some people call this skyscapering.
Skyscapering? Skyscrapering. Ed Lawrence,
my sensei from Creator
Booth, that's his term. Again,
I didn't steal it from him,
because I paid him
thousands and thousands of pounds.
Someone builds the tallest building in the
world.
Someone comes along and goes,
"Nice building, brother.
Let's make a taller one." Then a few years
later, someone sees that and goes, "Nice
building, brother.
Let's build a taller one." And over time,
all of
these buildings trying to out-skyscraper
each other in height create a
beautiful landscape of buildings
that we can look at as a skyline,
and that benefits everyone,
except the first person to build one.
Even now, the fact
that I'm waffling so much, this
is just benefiting my average
view duration. Now, the biggest lesson,
if you've made it this far through the
video,
is that you're probably just not
that good at creating
content yet. I,
the first time looking down the lens,
because what I'm doing right now
is staring into the abyss.
I can't see the lens.
I can't see myself with where I'm looking.
If I look at myself,
I end up looking up there,
and that's not very good at all.
There's a certain level of being a weirdo
that it takes to be able to look into
absolutely nothing
and talk proficiently like I am right now.
And it takes time to adapt to that.
It takes time to naturally break eye
contact so
people don't think you're a psycho.
It takes time to understand the best way
to structure something.
It takes time to have hand gestures
that aren't too much like Kamala
Harris.
"I was raised in a middle-class
household."
The gesturing, the speech, the cadence,
this all takes time.
Every black belt world champion in jujitsu
was once a shitty white belt.
Every single Olympian
that swims all once couldn't swim.
They had to have their little arm aids
and inflatable aids on.
Everyone is shite in the beginning.
I was shite for years because there
weren't channels like this to watch.
But if you persevere long enough at white
belt, you get to blue, then you get to
purple, then you get to brown. But
if you're not willing to suck for two
years,
you're never going to get the next
promotion.
If you can take all those lessons on
board, you'll hit 10,000, then 15,000,
then
20,000, then 25,000.
Then one video will hit 100,000,
and it'll be amazing for your
confidence. But ultimately,
the only way you get better at this
is by continuing to
do it.
I'm going to leave you with something
today.
This guy whose video I ripped off,
Jeremy Ethier, 21 million views.
Incorporating the routines- Great editing,
great interactions.
Would you fuck off, lads chat? But
if we go back to the same guy, this
guy with millions of views started off
with just one shot up against a whiteboard
with his baseball cap back to front.
Everyone has humble beginnings.
Even let's go to Renaissance Periodization
that's here below.
Let's go to the videos.
Let's go to the oldest.
This is Mike Israetel's early content on
social media.
It's him sat in front of a presentation
slideshow.
He's even got a full head of hair 12 years
ago.
So now when you watch his videos,
it's very easy to get deflated thinking,
"Oh my
God, how is this guy so good?
Look at this now, with a
beautiful little studio. Oh,
he's got great editing.
He's got nice lighting on his little dome
head." All of these people that are
better than you at creating content just
started earlier, and they all sucked for
long periods of time. And if you can,
and which you will, video by video, suck
less, you can accomplish amazing things.
So keep going.
Hopefully,
that's going to help you get towards your
first 10,000 views per video.
But if the challenge for you
is getting your first 10,000 followers,
well, there's
a slightly different rule set of things we
need to really make sure we avoid
getting there. And for that,
you're going to need this video right
here.
It's just as valuable as this one,
but I think I get my point across a lot
shorter,
so check it out.